<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Ed Mullen | Strategy &amp; Design</title>
    <link>http://edmullen.com</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 17:40:30 +0000</pubDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>HealthCare.gov</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/healthcaregov</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 17:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/healthcaregov</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;HealthCare.gov has become a household name, and not for all the right reasons. It is an educational resource helping all Americans know their healthcare options and rights. It is also the home of the Health Insurance Marketplace, the exchanges established under the Affordable Care Act. It is also a project that I have a long and deep personal connection to.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HealthCare.gov was not born at the time of its much-publicized problems in October 2013. It originally launched July 1, 2010 and was considered a good example of government service done right &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newrepublic.com/blog/jonathan-cohn/75988/hey-sometimes-government-works&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Over the next three years, it had a few significant releases and numerous minor improvements prior to a June 2013 re-launch and the introduction of the Health Insurance Marketplace in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I worked on both versions.&lt;/strong&gt; In 2010, after I posted an &lt;a href=&quot;/all/envisioning-a-health-insurance-exchange&quot;&gt;unsolicited concept piece&lt;/a&gt;, I was &lt;a href=&quot;/all/how-i-became-involved-with-healthcaregov&quot;&gt;asked to join the team&lt;/a&gt; creating what would become HealthCare.gov. In 2012, I was asked to come back and work on the next version. It has been the most challenging and most rewarding work I&amp;rsquo;ve been a part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare reform has been an unfortunately contentious topic. The animosity between the two sides is a driving contextual factor in the implementation of the Act. It makes many things more difficult than they would be otherwise. It&amp;rsquo;s useful to remember this reality when thinking about HealthCare.gov. For one, it makes talking about the project more complicated. In talking about my role, I&amp;rsquo;m limited in what I can say, so I&amp;rsquo;ll stick with information already publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;2012-13 &lt;span class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;(Version 2.0 / Exchange)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Initial involvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having played a significant role in the &lt;a href=&quot;#section-2&quot;&gt;first version of HealthCare.gov&lt;/a&gt;, I was asked in the fall of 2012 to work on similar aspects for the upcoming version, the launch of the Health Insurance Marketplace. A lot of work had been underway, particularly on the technical side. I was joining an effort to look at the overall experience and help make it as user-friendly as possible. Initially this involved: considering lessons learned from HealthCare.gov up to that point; understanding the new needs, requirements, difficulties, and context; and helping to shape a unified consumer-oriented experience within the current constraints. This took form as ideation and &lt;em&gt;broad-strokes&lt;/em&gt; design concepts, largely for discussion to aid decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sonya / design direction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-right&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_01&quot; alt=&quot;Sonya persona&quot;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sonya&amp;rdquo; as shown at SXSW 2013 &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/officialsxsw/the-innovation-data-health&quot;  target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I was part of a small sprint team tasked with setting the design direction of HealthCare.gov &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2013/06/healthcaregov-code-developed-by-the-people-and-for-the-people-released-back-to-the-people/277295/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Our purpose was to conceptually define how all consumer experiences could work together, from outreach, engagement, and education, through application and enrollment. This was done with a strict focus on the consumer, who we personified as &lt;em&gt;Sonya&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/officialsxsw/the-innovation-data-health#t=45:11&quot;  target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Production&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on the design direction, I worked with a number of people producing materials and design specifications for the development teams to use for two separate launches: the June educational/redesign launch and the October Marketplace launch. This involved the typical tasks of a user experience designer: coordination, planning, consensus-building across teams, development of wireframes, UI design planning, diagrams, explanatory materials, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Educational launch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2013, the HealthCare.gov redesign launched. This release was purely educational in nature, aimed at providing information and resources to people ahead of the Marketplace launch in October. It featured an entirely reimagined information architecture, dramatic simplification of content, new visual design and interaction patterns—particulary the navigation and &amp;ldquo;card, canvas, controls&amp;rdquo; motif—that anticipated the upcoming functionality of the Marketplace. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_02.png&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot&quot;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;February 2014 version of a &lt;em&gt;Learn&lt;/em&gt;-side article&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This launch went off without a hitch and the technology implemented continued to perform flawlessly in autumn despite the other problems that arose &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://developmentseed.org/blog/2013/10/24/its-called-jekyll/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Alex Howard &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2013/06/healthcaregov-code-developed-by-the-people-and-for-the-people-released-back-to-the-people/277295/&quot;&gt;profiled the launch&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;October Health Insurance Marketplace launch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the poor performance at launch, it must be said that no person involved with the October launch considers it close to satisfactory. It was a famously bad launch. &lt;em&gt;That said,&lt;/em&gt; I remain proud of the work I contributed to the effort and am happy to have been a part of the project as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked on UX design issues across the overall customer journey: from the planned anonymous browsing &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fiercegovernmentit.com/story/cms-official-healthcaregov-anonymous-browsing-function-failed-testing/2013-11-14&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to account creation to the application process to eligibility determination and the enrollment process. With others, I worked to create flows, transitions, tools, and processes that helped get people through a complicated set of constraints. With others, I tried to keep the focus on real people, with their own hectic lives, navigating a health care system that isn&amp;rsquo;t easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-column&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_03.png&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Screenshot of my own application&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_04.png&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Screenshot of my own application&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_05.png&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Screenshot of my own application&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_06.png&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Screenshot of my own application&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_07.png&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Screenshot of my own application&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_08.png&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Screenshot of my own application&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_09.png&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Screenshot of my own application&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;At launch, the results were almost entirely negative. But there are increasingly positive signs the live experience is getting closer to the designed experience.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far—I&amp;rsquo;m writing this mid-February—over 5 million people &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://acasignups.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; have enrolled in coverage through HealthCare.gov, making their way through a process with very complicated requirements. (Many more have enrolled through other methods.) About three-fifths of those have been people qualified for Medicaid, which means they were required to provide considerable financial and personal information. About two-thirds of the people end up getting coverage through private plans, with or without subsidies. The user experience is more complex for people who may be eligible for financial assistance or whose finincial situation is harder to determine because more information needs to be requested in order to check eligibility. People not seeking financial assistance have a shorter application. For people seeking private plans, there is the added complexity of choosing a plan that will be a good fit for their needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The images above are composite screenshots from my own HealthCare.gov application, through which I enrolled in coverage for my family. Our current plan will save us thousands over the plan we bought for ourselves last year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work with HealthCare.gov came to a close shortly after launch as planned. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;In closing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In writing this, I am trying to be straight. I am a pragmatic designer. I don&amp;rsquo;t aspire to make perfect little things. I aspire to participate in meaningful, impactful work; to contribute what I can to hopefully produce better outcomes than if I had not been involved. I won&amp;rsquo;t hide a year&amp;rsquo;s worth of hard work or disassociate myself with a project for convenience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also not interested in glossing over the thouroughly disappointing parts. There are many things that I&amp;rsquo;m not happy about. There have been victories and missed opportunities; mistakes in judgement and process as well as heroic efforts and brilliant contributions. I&amp;rsquo;m concurrently proud of the successes of HealthCare.gov and disappointed by the poor roll-out. Such is life, I guess. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;2010 &lt;span class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;(Version 1.0 / Initial Launch)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010, I was invited to join The U.S. Department of Health and Human Services team as design lead for HealthCare.gov, a new website mandated by the recently passed Affordable Care Act. (&lt;a href=&quot;/all/how-i-became-involved-with-healthcaregov&quot;&gt;How this came to be&lt;/a&gt; is a rather interesting story.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked to help the team define the scope and breadth of the site and how it might be structured. I created paper models to get the team on the same page, designed and presented solutions to leadership, created the visual style, and oversaw design production. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-column&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_10.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Sketches and early studies for architecture of site&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_11.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Sketches and early studies for architecture of site&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_12.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Sketches and early studies for architecture of site&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_13.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Sketches and early studies for architecture of site&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_14.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Integrated site architecture paper model&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_15.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Integrated site architecture paper model&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_16.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Anatomy of HealthCare.gov&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_17.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Homepage&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_18.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Finder&amp;rdquo; homepage: The process for discovering the options available to you is two short steps&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_19.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Menu of available options to you: This varies based on the answers you&amp;rsquo;ve submitted&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_20.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Private insurance plan listing&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_21.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Private insurance plan page based on existing research/subject matter expertise was field tested&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_22.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Audience-focused section&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_healthcaregov_body_23.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Timeline&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a whirlwind project, working closely with Todd Park, Macon Phillips, and the internal HHS team, we launched after only two months work on July 1, 2010. We rolled out updates over the next few months. After five months, I returned to the private sector and my own practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/06/healthcare-obama-entrepreneurs-twitter/&quot;&gt;VIDEO: Behind Healthcare.gov: How Washington Is Drawing Inspiration From Silicon Valley, Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Former White House Director of New Media, Macon Phillips, and Former U.S. Department of Health &amp;amp; Human Services CTO, Todd Park, discuss the process of bringing HealthCare.gov to life, how I came to be involved with the project, and my role in it. (TechCrunch/Evelyn Rusli)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-right&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/DCQSGnZ0lTg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;President Obama demos the 2010 launch of HealthCare.gov&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This initial version of HealthCare.gov was the first time ever citizens could view every individual private insurance option available to them in one place, as well as other healthcare programs. The site parsed billions of potential options and presented a usable menu of applicable healthcare options tailored to the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch went well and received largely favorable reviews: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=128232529&amp;amp;ft=1&amp;amp;f=1027&quot;&gt;NPR&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://swampland.blogs.time.com/2010/07/01/healthcare-gov-launches/?artId=28494?contType=blog_swampland?chn=us&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.consumerreports.org/health/2010/07/ask-nancy-where-can-i-find-good-health-insurance.html&quot;&gt;Consumer Reports&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/06/30/AR2010063005308.html&quot;&gt;The Washington Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/2010/0701/Healthcare.gov-How-to-figure-out-your-health-care-options&quot;&gt;The Christian Science Monitor&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kaiserhealthnews.org/Stories/2010/July/01/hhs-website-health-insurance.aspx&quot;&gt;Kaiser Health News&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503544_162-20009427-503544.html?tag=mncol;lst;1&quot;&gt;CBS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/07/01/healthcaregov-new-governm_n_632365.html&quot;&gt;Huffington Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://voices.washingtonpost.com/ezra-klein/2010/07/healthcaregov.html&quot;&gt;Ezra Klein&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tnr.com/blog/jonathan-cohn/75988/hey-sometimes-government-works&quot;&gt;Jonathan Cohn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/craig-newmark/healthcaregov----real-inf_b_632035.html&quot;&gt;Craig Newmark&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.politicsdaily.com/2010/07/01/healthcare-gov-the-government-is-here-to-help-really/&quot;&gt;Jill Lawrence&lt;/a&gt;, and others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;quiet&quot;&gt;Photo at top CC BY 2.0 by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/daveynin/7417095278/&quot;&gt;David Fulmer&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ReliefWeb / UN OCHA</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/reliefweb-un-ocha</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2014 16:03:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/reliefweb-un-ocha</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;ReliefWeb is a leading news and information channel for humanitarians worldwide. It is the UN&amp;rsquo;s most visited website. The service collects and vets content from the UN, Governments, NGOs, nonprofits and other sources about crises and natural disasters from countries around the globe to create the most complete picture of those events.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Charting a course forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I collaborated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cairnsim&quot;&gt;Ian Cairns&lt;/a&gt; to develop a product roadmap that included immediate design and development actions as well as medium- and long-term strategic planning to help ReliefWeb meet the needs of its humanitarian audience for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reliefweb.int&quot;&gt;Visit ReliefWeb.int&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-right&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;report cover&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple years prior to my involvement, Ian had worked with ReliefWeb when he was at &lt;a href=&quot;http://developmentseed.org/&quot;&gt;DevelopmentSeed&lt;/a&gt;. DevSeed helped ReliefWeb undergo a major platform relaunch; restructuring the experience and underlying technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After focusing on content and editorial efforts for two years, it became clear that ReliefWeb was ready to take the next step of their evolution. ReliefWeb reached out to Ian, and he asked me to team up to develop a product roadmap that would guide the team over the next several years. The vision that emerged was a “one-stop-shop” for the global humanitarian community, while remaining mindful of the important mission laid out for ReliefWeb after the Rwandan genocide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Big Picture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary goal for the project was to define a clear path forward. Defining what “ReliefWeb” meant became important. Internally ‘ReliefWeb’ had been synonymous with both the team and the Web offering. Shifting to a product-focused mindset allowed the team to see that their various products could have a variety of trajectories, including those that led towards collaboration with other teams within the UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA). Helping to articulate this concept, as well as visualizing the eventual convergence was critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_01&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Excerpt from &amp;ldquo;ReliefWeb: Vision &amp; Strategy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_02&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Excerpt from &amp;ldquo;ReliefWeb: Vision &amp; Strategy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/a/reliefweb.int/file/d/0B-95ZTCMjvgSa3l0OFlyMHJ1WlU/&quot;&gt;“ReliefWeb: Vision &amp;amp; Strategy”&lt;/a&gt; (Made available publicly by ReliefWeb.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blog post on ReliefWeb.int:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://reliefweb.int/blogpost/year-hub-introducing-reliefweb-roadmap&quot;&gt;The Year of the Hub: Introducing the ReliefWeb roadmap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Design Evolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ReliefWeb.int was a well-functioning site that didn’t need complete redesign. What it needed was iterative, ongoing improvement to allow the property to become increasingly rich over time. In establishing a roadmap for the product, short-, medium-, and long-term improvements were planned. Some of the short-term improvements involved revising the reading and browsing experience and improving the way ReliefWeb talked about itself and presented its offerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_03&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Updated homepage&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_04&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Updated article page&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_05&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;New &amp;ldquo;About&amp;rdquo; page&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_06&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;New &amp;ldquo;About&amp;rdquo; page&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;New Content Formats&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ReliefWeb team compiles huge amounts of high-quality information that helps humanitarians make sense of conditions across the globe. While examining the &lt;em&gt;raw material&lt;/em&gt; that is produced, new opportunities for ReliefWeb.int became clear. These include shorter-term mash-ups of existing content such as Topic Pages–designed to allow humanitarians with specializations such as &lt;em&gt;nutrition&lt;/em&gt;, to follow the latest developments within that specialization–as well as longer-term planning for telling richer stories around countries, crises, and disasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_07&quot; alt=&quot;New &quot;Topic&quot; pages&quot;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;New &amp;ldquo;Topic&amp;rdquo; pages&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Process &amp;amp; Exploration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each step in a product’s evolution can’t be perfectly planned and predicted. Finding ways for high-profile organizations like ReliefWeb to feel comfortable experimenting can be challenging. ReliefWeb Labs addresses this need. The Labs provides cover to try things out. It also establishes a product development process to move successful products or features from idea, to testable prototype, to full integration with the primary products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_09&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;New blog&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_reliefweb_body_08&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Introduced ReliefWeb Labs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;UN Resolution 51/194&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 February 1997&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The General Assembly, …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;… Reaffirming the need for the improved accountability of all relevant actors involved in emergency relief operations, …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;… 13. Requests the Secretary-General to further develop Reliefweb as the global humanitarian information system for the dissemination of reliable and timely information on emergencies and natural disasters, and encourages all Governments, the United Nations agencies, funds and programmes and other relevant organizations, including non-governmental organizations, to support Reliefweb and actively participate in the Reliefweb information exchange, through the Department of Humanitarian Affairs;”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;quiet&quot;&gt;Photo at top: Displaced families with Nyiragongo volcano at the back by Mugunga III IDPs camp which hosts some 30,000 people. Source: OCHA Gemma Cortes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MixTrail</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/mixtrail</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2014 16:14:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/mixtrail</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-right&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_mixtrail_body_08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MixTrail logo&quot; style=&quot;border:0; padding-top: 2.25rem;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;MixTrail was a system for connecting great content from across the web to tell big stories. &amp;ldquo;Trails&amp;rdquo; were made by people drawing connections between pages on different sites. Readers could then move sequentially along the trail, website to website, gaining a broader view of a topic or idea than is available within a single site. I conceived and designed MixTrail and Robb Smylie built it. For &lt;a href=&quot;#putting-it-on-ice&quot;&gt;a number of reasons&lt;/a&gt;, the project has been put on indefinite hold.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;1. The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been concerned that our emphasis on “the stream” — news, timely information, ephemeral content — leaves us knowing where we are but not how we got here. Many of the tools we&amp;rsquo;ve created help us find specific answers, but not broader ideas or truths. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_mixtrail_body_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Disconnected content illustration&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is not a lack of great content; the problem (or one of the problems) is that the great content is disconnected from its larger context, spread across the web, frequently languishing in websites that are not always the best custodians of that content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-idea&quot;&gt;2. The Idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MixTrail provided a platform for people to share what they&amp;rsquo;ve learned about a topic by connecting meaningful content into brief &amp;ldquo;trails&amp;rdquo;. Readers could then follow those trails between content spread across various sites the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_mixtrail_body_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Connected content illustration&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In creating these trails people built cross-site sequences, expanding the orginial &lt;strong&gt;1&amp;rarr;2&lt;/strong&gt; relationship of hyperlinks into the &lt;strong&gt;1&amp;larr;&amp;rarr;2&amp;larr;&amp;rarr;3&amp;larr;&amp;rarr;4&amp;larr;&amp;rarr;5&amp;larr;&amp;rarr;6&amp;larr;&amp;rarr;7&lt;/strong&gt; relationship of trails. Once these connections are defined, there are a number of possibilities.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The long, early version&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentation below from March 2011, lays out the product vision. As a presentation, its far too long, but at the time I wanted to lay out the full big idea. The deck explains the problem, the concept of a trail, viewing a trail, discovering trails, how trails are created, trail maintenance, following trails, and platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;script async class=&quot;speakerdeck-embed&quot; data-id=&quot;d55d17c090400131ed397a557317c4b7&quot; data-ratio=&quot;1.2994923857868&quot; src=&quot;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The short, later version&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months later I created a streamlined version of the deck. It focused more on the people who might use MixTrail and was intended to serve as a conversation prop, rather than house all the content itself. The screens included show the more stripped down launch functionality. Originally this was a Keynote presentation with animations that mimicked the actual experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;script async class=&quot;speakerdeck-embed&quot; data-id=&quot;f1faec7090430131ed397a557317c4b7&quot; data-ratio=&quot;1.33333333333333&quot; src=&quot;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Teaser&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a public teaser trailer from mid-2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/40036423?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-observations&quot;&gt;3. Key Observations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Great content on any topic is available from multiple sources.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best information on any given topic is usually spread between multiple sources, yet those sources are often disinclined to send their audience to a &lt;em&gt;competitor&lt;/em&gt;. This relates to &lt;em&gt;Joy&amp;rsquo;s Law&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;ldquo;No matter who you are, most of the smartest people work for someone else.&amp;rdquo; MixTrail embraced the distributed nature of great content creators, producers, and publications and proposed a solution for bringing that content together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Constraints are an important aspect of curation.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bookmarking tools are one method of &lt;em&gt;bucketing&lt;/em&gt; content by topic. A big limitation with this sort of unconstrained collection is that the bucket never fills up. You&amp;rsquo;re not forced to make any decisions. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to choose between keeping &lt;em&gt;Article A&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Article B&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_mixtrail_body_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The trail view window shows the seven pages (or less) contained in the trail and a bit of information of how each page fits within the larger whole.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MixTrail limited the length of trails to seven and required thought about the sequence of steps. The idea was that these constraints force decisions akin to a gallery curator who has limited wall space and must choose which pictures will make the best exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Human curation is important.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a lot of value in the deliberative process of thinking about a topic, gathering important resources on it, providing one&amp;rsquo;s personal observations and reactions to those resources, and then sharing that body of work. MixTrail facilitated this age-old practice. A lot could have been done with the aggregate data, but at its heart, MixTrail was about people sharing big stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Design of the content is part of the content.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re getting better at producing solid digital-first content that seeks to be more than text on a screen. Increasingly this means embracing rich content, video, data, or interactive components to tell a full story. The way we design our content influences its meaning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_mixtrail_body_04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot showing page with meaningful design choices&quot;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Longform content often is intentionally designed to aide its consumption.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was important that MixTrail allowed you to move between individual pieces of content while retaining the design. Sometimes stripping the cruft out of busy websites (as &lt;em&gt;read it later&lt;/em&gt; tools like Instapaper or Pocket do) is helpful, but other times it destroys the original intent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Content creators are not always the best stewards of their own content.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are still living in the period when much of the best content on the web comes from people or organizations heavily influenced by print precursors. This can mean that the forms that content is put into derive from pre-web analogs. It can mean the publishing tools or thinking is print-first (write in Word, save to PDF). It can mean that organizations have strict divisions of responsibility between those who produce content and those who &amp;ldquo;put it on the web&amp;rdquo;. In most cases, people publish something then forget it, moving on to the next piece and leaving any ongoing care for the content to the &amp;ldquo;web people&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;4. Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked on MixTrail on and off for about two years, starting in late 2010 and ending in late 2012. Most of the time I was also working on client work; sometimes there were weeks or months when I exclusively focused on MixTrail. For the first half I mostly worked on it alone, the second half I was collaborating with Robb. There were three roughly equivalent phases to MixTrail&amp;rsquo;s progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Figuring it out.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phase was about understanding the problem, finding potential solutions, and figuring out how to talk about the two. All of my previous work reinforced the feeling that there was a missing piece of the plumbing of the web; connective tissue that did not exist. Getting my head around the problem and assigning some shape to it that would allow me to discuss it with others was my first goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img_mixtrail_body_06.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_mixtrail_body_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Whiteboard drawing&quot; style=&quot;border:0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Defining a product.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second phase was focused on defining the product and figuring out how to make it. At the same time I was learning more about lean thinking, start-up methodologies and philosophies, and familiarizing myself with the world of raising capital should it be necessary. I defined the overall product vision, tried to convince Robb to participate, worked with Robb preparing for development after he agreed to be my partner, worked back from the larger vision to identify a minimum viable product, and designed the first release version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img_mixtrail_body_07.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_mixtrail_body_07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Information architecture diagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Building it.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third phase mostly involved building the system. What Robb built and deployed was very complex. There were extensive account, editing, and admin requirements. The viewing experience provided a number of challenges. Even though we were focusing on the mimimun functionality we felt was necessary to express the intention of the system, it was still extensive. But Robb pulled it off while doing all the other things in his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While he built, I tried to sort out issues on the business side: roll-out strategies, refining the pitch, learning about possible funding opportunities. Robb finished the aplha release. There were aspects we weren&amp;rsquo;t quite satisfied with but felt it was best to get it out in the world and start having people use it. But shortly after, things changed&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;putting-it-on-ice&quot;&gt;5. Putting It on Ice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, there were three main reasons that we set MixTrail aside and moved on to other things. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Experience issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a few aspects of the user experience that were difficult to overcome. The biggest challenge involved cross-domain issues. Our concept of having a navigational component that traveled with you as you moved from site to site utilized some methods that are also used for nefarious purposes in &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clickjacking&quot;&gt;clickjacking&lt;/a&gt;. To combat clickjacking, several big sites employ &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Framekiller&quot;&gt;framebusting techniques&lt;/a&gt;, which, for MixTrail, meant people would get thrown off their trail. We weren&amp;rsquo;t able to solve this fast enough in a way that was good enough for users. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Business model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially I wanted to just pursue the idea wherever it went. As the product was built, we came to see that the idea of simply bootstrapping the project seemed unsustainable. We were filling our nights and weekends and there was no immediate revenue stream to start underwriting our efforts. We began to explore the idea of raising money, but that wasn&amp;rsquo;t particularly attractive either. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, life sometimes comes into play. Robb&amp;rsquo;s second daughter was on the way; mine was very young. Then I got the call to rejoin the &lt;a href=&quot;/all/healthcaregov&quot;&gt;HealthCare.gov effort&lt;/a&gt;. At first I thought it might be ideal. But working mostly on HealthCare.gov and partly on MixTrail turned out to not be realistic. HealthCare.gov was taking up all my time. I realized that I felt the success of HealthCare.gov was more important than the success of MixTrail. If a founder&amp;rsquo;s project doesn&amp;rsquo;t take first priority in the founder&amp;rsquo;s mind, there is a problem, especially if you are considering asking for other people&amp;rsquo;s money to fund it. At that point it seemed right to put the project on hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having fully built the initial release and only releasing it to a handful of people, we gradually stopped working on it. A few months later we took the site down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;6. Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the ideas MixTrail sought to address remain front and center in my mind. People continue to produce great content in an increasingly fractured web landscape. As digital-first producers rise to prominence, the quality of the work is increasing. The converse is true too; more and more noise and clickbait competes for attention. Finding ways to connect the good stuff, navigate around the fluff, and become better informed people remains very, very important.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terrapin Bright Green</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/terrapin-bright-green</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 11:52:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/terrapin-bright-green</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Terrapin works to create a sustainable built environment through holistic design solutions inspired by the natural world they seek to preserve.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terrapin is an environmental consulting and strategic planning group that helps its clients think differently about environmental strategy, policy, and related opportunities. They help governments and planners create greener cities. They help architects and developers implement green methods in the projects the build. They help businesses fundamentally change the way they do business. And they do it all with a refreshing “change is both possible and practical” attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;Redesign 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-right&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_terrapin_body_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;report cover&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seven years, the time has come to reassess Terrapin&amp;rsquo;s website needs. I have recently completed a discovery and strategy project, working with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.casjam.com&quot;&gt;Brian Casel&lt;/a&gt;, that has defined a roadmap that is currently under development. More details after launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;Initial Launch 2007&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Connect big ideas to diverse projects in different business sectors.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terrapin is a company of big ideas and new ways of thinking. The heart of their practice is the marriage of sophisticated theoretical ideas and practical business virtues. Understanding that “green” is often misappropriated, Terrapin guides clients towards an understanding that environmentally minded measures pay strong business, productivity and community dividends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_terrapin_body_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;The interactive feature draws connections between big ideas, project categories and past client work. Content is pulled from a database and tied to the CMS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_terrapin_body_02.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;This approach allows users to navigate based on their motivations and find content that is relevant but they might have overlooked otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_terrapin_body_03.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Terrapin emphasizes collaboration. Their clients span the spectrum of the built environement and Terrapin works differently to meet each groups specific needs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_terrapin_body_04.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Terrapin&amp;rsquo;s story is best told through the work they&amp;rsquo;ve done and expereriences they&amp;rsquo;ve had. Publicly visible case studies showcase the highest profile examples.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interactive component featured prominently on the homepage helps visitors gain understanding of how lofty ideas such as “biomimicry” and “transcending the cost barrier” have been applied to specific projects in representative categories. This tool helps visitors see themselves in Terrapin’s solutions and become familiar with ideas that impact their own projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Provide hand-selected, relevant content to qualified visitors.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terrapin is led by pioneers in the green building movement. Their work is extremely extensive and wide ranging. By creating a private “Workroom” section of the site, Terrapin is able to vet visitors interested in learning more about the company, and easily generate a custom selection of projects that are relevant to the specific interests of that visitor. Content is selected from a collection of existing project profiles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_terrapin_body_05.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Workroom&amp;rdquo; provides a behind-the-scenes look at projects either lightly covered in the public area or completely hidden.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a government official who focuses on housing issues wants to learn more, they will be shown relevant government and housing projects and not be burdened muddling through large-scale corporate project. The amount of work required to set up an account is minimal, yet the visitor gains a more personal understanding of how Terrapin can address their needs and Terrapin comes away with a qualified lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;quiet&quot;&gt;Photo at top: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/rlerdorf/&quot;&gt;Rasmus Lerdorf&lt;/a&gt; CC BY 2.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free People</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/free-people</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 15:55:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/free-people</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Free People and Edward Mullen Studios have been collaborating for years. We have worked together on projects of varying size and complexity. The three projects included here are earlier examples of our work together. The two retail projects have now been supplanted by the more recent FreePeople.com redesign. The blog has been redesigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2006, Free People has partnered with Edward Mullen Studio to design the e-commerce experience for their constantly evolving and shifting brand. Free People is a young woman’s clothier with a focus on creativity, travel, and global style. Their clothes draw inspiration from around the world and attract fans interested in expressing themselves through Free People’s dramatic style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through several generations of their Web properties, the goal has been to create experiences that feel expressive, handcrafted, and special. Earlier versions focused on creating forms that felt uncommon in the e-commerce space. More recent efforts have focused on drawing in Free People fans to build collections and community around the brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fpme&quot;&gt;FPme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012 I worked with Free People in defining and designing their new social app and experience, FPme. I&amp;rsquo;ll post some information on that work as soon as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;retail&quot;&gt;Retail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through several generations of their main retail website, the goal has been to create experiences that feel expressive, handcrafted, and special. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Site Redesign - 2009/2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009 a major effort began to to optimize and modernize the entire shopping experience, layer in social activitity, and begin to integrate some emerging responsive web design techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Create a framework that allows for dramatic stylistic changes while retaining a consistent structure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free People is all about creativity and expression. They change and evolve faster than other brands. In order to embody this philosophy, the website experience had to allow for the same type of freedom and flexibility. A structural framework established a method that allows Free People&amp;rsquo;s in-house designers to change the aesthetics of the site while retaining a consistent layout and user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;The design framework allows for dramatic stylistic shifts with minimal effort.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_02.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;The design framework allows for dramatic stylistic shifts with minimal effort.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Embrace the wisdom of the crowd&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A social shopping component allows shoppers to assemble collections of their favorite Free People clothing. These collections can be viewed and shared with other shoppers to build bonds and inspire outfits. Product detail pages feature collections in which the item is included. Shoppers can follow their favorite stylists as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_20.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;A Collection&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_21.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Social user-generated Collections&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;A responsive shopping experience&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding that shoppers were viewing the website on different types of screens and devices, we wanted to be sure each person was having an optimum experience. Depending on the monitor size, the site contents are displayed differently. We also provided a number of viewing options for shoppers to choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_30.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Products can be viewed in a &amp;ldquo;collage&amp;rdquo; format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_31.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Viewers with smaller screens are presented a reduced-width format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_32.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Products can also be viewed in a traditional grid format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_33.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;The framework allows for easy reconfiguration of product image sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_34.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;The framework allows for easy reconfiguration of product image sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_35.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Product detail page&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;A streamlined mobile experience that maintains the Free People style&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dedicated mobile site used dynamic elements gracefully; understanding they should add value and not complicate the shopping experience for people who don&amp;rsquo;t make use of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_40.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Accommodate a growing brand family&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free People is the fastest growing brand within the Urban Outfitters family. This growth led to experimentations with two new Free People brands, beside the main Free People Collection. The framework was built in a way that allowed Free People to create separately branded shopping experiences at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_50.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Optimized checkout experience&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on observation of behavior, the checkout process was optimized to improve conversions and streamline the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_60.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Checkout process optimization wireframe&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_61.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Checkout process optimization wireframe&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_62.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Checkout process optimization - User flow chart&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_63.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Checkout process optimization&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_64.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Checkout process optimization&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Site Refresh - 2007&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an on-going effort to increase the beauty, fun and functionality of the Free People retail site, an interim redesign effort was undertaken with the aim of retro-fitting the existing site to add increased flexibility for exciting, unexpected visual and interactive surprises and increase conversion through a reconfiguration of the product detail page. This site was replaced with an earlier version of the current website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_70.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2006 - not launched&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, Free People began the process of redesigning their Retail eCommerce website. The site was designed as an online corollary to the Free People aesthetic. The site was heavily styled and intended to break away from the prevailing format of eCommerce sites at the time. Great effort was taken to find ways of looking different yet remaining usable. In the end, the project was set aside due to business needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_80.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Product detail page&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_retail_body_81.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Shopping cart page&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wholesale&quot;&gt;Wholesale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a brand grows, it can struggle to maintain it&amp;rsquo;s original touch. Free People sought to extend the showroom/buyer experience to broader audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free People originated as a wholesale business. Today they have a fast growing retail business, both online and in Free People branded boutiques across the country. Yet their wholesale division continues to expand. Free People decided to develop a site that would allow buyers and reps to conduct their business online in a branded environment that paid homage to the experience buyers have when they go to the NY, Chicago or L.A. showrooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Establish a design framework that allows for dramatic visual variation over time with minimal workload requirements.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By creating a stylistically neutral site structure and pairing it with the use of big, loud, dramatic photographs that change with each visit, the site style takes on that of the photography. This allows Free People to highlight the amazing work being done all over their Philly Navy Yard home offices by the artists and designers that make Free People the fun, playful company that it is. An honest “brand expression” simply reflects the true nature of the company. Here we are infusing the buyers with the Free People spirit they are looking to share with their customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_wholesale_body_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_wholesale_body_02.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Create an experience that goes beyond a typical e-commerce site and engages in the type of experience buyers have when they are in a showroom.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When buyers shop Free People showrooms or trade show booths, they both actively flip through racks of clothing or have an arrangement of items presented to them. They are often accompanied by the representative and maintain a relationship with that individual. These were ideas that were important to retain. Utilizing a photo slideshow motif, familiar to them from photo sharing websites, buyers have the ability to watch the items as an animated slideshow, view items as a linear stream of products or dig deep and get down to business in single product format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_wholesale_body_03.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;In addition to the typical product grid, buyers can view products in a format similar to photo sharing sites, or view an animated slideshow of products in a given category.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_wholesale_body_04.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Buyers are able to create and share lists of favorite items, and representatives are able to recommend list of items they believe fit well within their store based on past purchase history and experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Provide buyers and their representatives with information and tools that will ease the process of managing existing orders and making new ones.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wholesale orders are much more complex than regular e-commerce interaction. Buyers are purchasing multiples of individual styles, in a variety of sizes and colors, some of which have order minimums or other restrictions. It was important to make these complexities understandable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_wholesale_body_05.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;At any time, buyers can open the details pane and begin ordering their items. They can always utlilize the thumbnail stream to jump forward and back in the line-up of products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_wholesale_body_06.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;The shopping basket sorts items into delivery (release) dates, and applies any rules associated with each. Requirements for wholesale shopping can be complex, but are clearly communicated to buyers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_wholesale_body_07.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Invoices clearly document orders and are archived for future reference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_wholesale_body_08.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Shipping information is also more complex than a typical e-commerce scenario. Orders are usually broken into many shipments. Understand what items are coming and when is vital for store owners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_wholesale_body_09.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Representatives have quick access to deep knowledge on the purchasing history of their clients, helping them make better recommendations on new orders and answer client inquiries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing placed orders is also complex. Styles are released at different dates and vary in availability. A single order may contain items from several delivery categories, with individual items on backorder or shipping at different times. Wholesale buyers were given the ability to easily check to see where their orders were, which items haves shipped and how the orders are broken into multiple shipments when necessary. Representatives can get deep account information and put together presentations of recommended garments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blog&quot;&gt;Caravan of Curiosities blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free People is an odd company. It is chock-full of creative, happy, artsy folks working in a supportive and stimulating environment making imaginative, expressive clothes for girls who just don’t want to fade into the background. The Caravan is a place where Free People gets to share the things they like (music, artists, videos), conduct craft swaps and give an inside look at FP designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_blog_body_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_blog_body_02.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_blog_body_03.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_free-people_blog_body_04.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oberlin College &amp; Conservatory</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/oberlin</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 21:31:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/oberlin</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Oberlin College is a leading, historic Liberal Arts College and Conservatory of Music in Oberlin, Ohio. I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with Oberlin on a number of projects over the years.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;Oberlin Illuminate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012 I created the &lt;a href=&quot;http://campaign.oberlin.edu&quot;&gt;companion website&lt;/a&gt; to Oberlin College&amp;rsquo;s capital campaign, with help from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brucetangdesign.com/&quot;&gt;Bruce Tang&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.casjam.com&quot;&gt;Brial Casel&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about the project as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;Oberlin.edu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a period of change and transition, Oberlin undertook the task of redeveloping their network of Web properties to address the needs of the thriving institution and create a modern, vibrant public-facing representation of the two schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_oberlin_body_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_oberlin_body_02.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_oberlin_body_03.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_oberlin_body_04.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_oberlin_body_05.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_oberlin_body_06.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_oberlin_body_07.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Oberlin project, like all higher education websites, came with a set of complex needs from a variety of stakeholders. These included: marketing and outreach to prospective students and future community members; individual requirements from a variety of programs within the school; upholding the strong traditions of an institution with a rich history; establishing flexibility and creating a scalable framework for future growth; tying into existing marketing efforts and general brand guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding a balance with solutions that satisfy all parties was the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create a unified institutional presence while allowing for variation between appropriate areas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A design framework was established that provides a contextual understanding of the content and a hierarchical structure that varies the experience of using the site. Color coding of sections reinforces school (and site) organization, expresses difference between areas and unifies through consistent intensity. Color is a vehicle for expressing the vibrancy of the school. The boldness, and its acceptance, says a lot about the confidence of the school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The story of Oberlin is best expressed through its students&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homepage features an interactive component that tells the Oberlin story through the successes and experiences of current and former students. These stories are pulled from a growing pool of stories and change with each visit. Visitors can dig deeper and find out more about each story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Establish efficient navigation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global navigation element at the top of all pages reduces visual clutter yet provides deep access into the two schools, the two shared campus sections (student life and campus activities), quick access to the admissions areas and links to the main college services. The header can be implemented in multiple formats, allowing for different uses based on the context and the ability to tie external sites into the new Oberlin scheme. Below this global header, there is a correpsonding internal structural system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;quiet&quot;&gt;Photo at top: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/edsel_/5776689034/&quot;&gt;Edsel Little&lt;/a&gt; CC BY 2.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stone Barns Center for Food &amp; Agriculture</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/stone-barns-center-for-food-agriculture</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 21:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/stone-barns-center-for-food-agriculture</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;The Stone Barns Center for Food &amp;amp; Agriculture is a regional leader in public advocacy and the education of sustainable farming practices. The New York farm is spread over 80 acres of beautiful countryside on a former Rockefeller estate.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four-season working farm is open to the public, home to the world famous Blue Hill at Stone Barns, and the site of year-round consumer and farmer educational activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Design Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone Barns sought to investigate opportunities for online activity in line with their strategic direction. Given that the project revolves around future efforts, few details can be shared. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_stonebarns_body_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Vision &amp; Tactics for the Web strategy document&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_stonebarns_body_02.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Persona usecases&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_stonebarns_body_03.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Site Map&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_stonebarns_body_04.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Third-party technology assessment&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_stonebarns_body_05.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Systems documentation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_stonebarns_body_06.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Appendix&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_stonebarns_body_07.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Extensive wireframe development&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_stonebarns_body_08.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Requirements document&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is safe to say that the project involved extensive investigation, strategic vision, and detailed tactical direction. Activities included stakeholder interviews, content strategy, technological assessment, internal productivity assessment, workload issues, extensive information architectural planning, and the creation of detailed wireframes and documentation providing Stone Barns with a detailed blueprint for future efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making Things In Government and Out</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/making-things-in-government-and-out</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 13:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/making-things-in-government-and-out</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Danny Chapman got me thinking. He asked, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dannychapman.com/2013/07/01/makers-of-things/&quot;&gt;“What would it be like if our legislative bodies were more balanced between lawyers and people who make things we interact with every day - designers, entrepreneurs and engineers?”&lt;/a&gt; Better, for sure. I don’t know what it would take for that to come about, but having people who are thinking about the experience of the implemented law would definitely make the experiences better.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I started thinking about how things are made now. Making things inside government is different than making things outside of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not in the camp that believes the private sector is a panacea. There are problems in the private sector just as in the public sector. Most of my career has been outside of government, and I haven’t experienced a perfect project yet. But I believe that an awareness of the context within which you are making something helps make that thing better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve made things in both worlds. In the hope that they may be helpful in improving the making of things within government, I thought I’d lay out some of my observations about the differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;Product/Market Fit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key concepts in the startup world is the idea of “product/market fit”. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20070701074943/http://blog.pmarca.com/2007/06/the-pmarca-gu-2.html&quot;&gt;Marc Andreessen has said&lt;/a&gt;, “Product/market fit means being in a good market with a product that can satisfy that market.” You should be willing to explore various combinations of product features and offerings that address the needs of potential audiences and markets, but you should also be willing to abandon certain audiences if others prove more fruitful. Success can be defined as finding ‘fit’, regardless of whether the initial problem or need the product set out to fix ever got solved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the world of government, there is frequently less flexibility. “Product” and “market” can’t be so casually discarded. The product mission is often largely predetermined, seeking to address a societal ill or neglected ‘market’. There is a fixed need in search of a solution, not an open search for new product opportunities. The market is also less flexible. Government organizations often have specific constituencies that must be served. So there is a responsibility to address particular needs for a particular audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That still leaves opportunity for exploring different approaches and tactics to address the needs. Variables still exist, and the iterative, quick learning approaches of ‘lean’ are helpful. Sometimes; however, policy decisions are put in place that require very specific methods. These fixed variables reduce the product’s flexibility, even while delivering some policy benefit to a constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when making things within government, there is usually fewer variables to play with, and more constraints to work around. That’s not an indictment, just context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;The Founder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the implications of ‘lean’ thinking that has bothered me is the almost mercenary attitude of finding any ol’ unaddressed market and exploiting it. At times it can feel like the application of a process without being invested in fixing a specific problem. (Insert silly pivot story here.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there’s nothing wrong with this, it seems a bit boring. It also seems out-of-step with the mission-oriented spirit of those in government, or other civic hackers, working to resolve specific issues for the betterment of the larger community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not true of all startups. Many of the best startups begin with a founder with a keen insight into a particular audience or need. While that founder may lead his or her team through many iterations towards a goal, there usually is a goal. The thing that drives the founder toward the goal is passion. It’s a passion that says, “I may not know exactly how we’re going to get there, but I know where we need to go. Let’s figure it out.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That founder probably started out on his/her own, or with another founder or two. Cobbling something together, probably while working on something else. At some point, he or she just had to put it into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be tricky to replicate that critical role within government, but it’s important to try. The vision of a founder can be critical at many junctures; points where going down the wrong path could be hard to recover from; points where a fight is needed. This is true inside and outside of government. Having someone in a position that fully embodies the thing that’s being made is important to making sure it‘s made right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-3&quot;&gt;The Client/Vendor Relationship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both inside and outside of government, organizations choose between whether they will make stuff themselves with their own staff or whether they will hire outside vendors to make the stuff for them. Frequently there is a mix of internal people and external people. Regardless of the context, this choice has an impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are business reasons for choosing one over the other. Sometimes the resources needed to hire staff are too great and don’t make long-term sense. Other times the organization doesn’t value the skillset that the vendor brings enough to hire internally. And other times the need is temporary and a vendor makes perfect sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the more a product becomes part of the core function of an organization, as it does in a “digital by default” context, the more important it becomes for the organization to live and breathe the product and understand all of its intricate inner workings. It becomes critical to have institutional knowledge that can remind the team why a certain decision was made, assess the wisdom of that decision against ongoing learning, and adjust based on the full knowledge of where the product started, what’s been successful, and where it’s going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is somewhat awkward for me to say because I’m on the vendor side most of the time. Regardless of whether you are internal or external, you want the stuff you make to be a success. When some significant portion of the team that makes something is going to leave after a certain milestone, it’s critical to find ways to internalize the ideas and knowledge of those folks, so that the people who remain will be able to evolve the product with the full body of knowledge that went into making the thing in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-4&quot;&gt;Acquisitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Innovation is tricky everywhere. Any organization can become stale (and usually does at times). Sometimes what the organization really needs is an injection of outside innovation. Everyone knows that hiring and procurement is far harder inside government. So is firing. While this prevents a lot of cronyism, it also makes it harder to get that extra boost that a particular person or team could really add to the internal team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies outside of government can hire freely and bring in folks who they know are needed on their team. But another way a lot of companies develop innovative products is by buying them, sometimes for boatloads of money. They watch startups trying things out. Most fail. Some don’t. When something catches, they buy them out. Usually the founders and key people need to stick around for a couple years to institutionalize the mojo that made the product successful and frequently to spread that mojo around other internal products that have lost their own. But after some time those people leave and go build private spaceship companies or other products that they are curious about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a process that is trickier to emulate within government. The government can’t acquire a company. Besides, they probably wouldn’t want to. But that churn in and out is a helpful one that is harder for government to benefit from. The Presidential Innovation Fellows program and similar programs are a great start. Other means of hiring people for two or three year stints could also be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-5&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m of the firm belief that government can and does do great work. It does things and solves problems that other people don’t care about. It’s just important to recognize that the context of making things within the government is different. If you’re making things within government, you should have a clear head about what works outside of it, what works inside of it, and how the best of both can be brought to bear in that unique context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to hear if you’ve had experiences making things inside and outside of government. What are the differences you’ve witnessed? Have you learned ways of spreading the good from one into the other?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;quiet&quot;&gt;Photo CC BY 2.0 by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/timpatterson/476098132/sizes/o/&quot;&gt;Tim Patterson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Ed Mullen</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/about/about-ed-mullen</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2014 16:56:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/about/about-ed-mullen</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;In the most simplistic sense, I design websites and other digital experiences, but I consider myself a designer in the broadest sense of the word. I work with people from many kinds of organizations to help them solve problems that are holding them back.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through strategic thinking and pragmatic design, I aim to amplify the impact of people doing good work in the world. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/all/healthcaregov&quot;&gt;Enrolling millions of people&lt;/a&gt; in health coverage (HealthCare.gov)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evolving a &lt;a href=&quot;/all/reliefweb-un-ocha&quot;&gt;global humanitarian information resource&lt;/a&gt; (UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs&amp;#39; ReliefWeb.int)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helping innovators create a move sustainable built environment (Terrapin)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am based in Jersey City, NJ (near NYC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Activities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My projects often entail investigating an organization&amp;rsquo;s needs and objectives, defining a strategy to meet the objectives, developing tactics and methods for implementing the strategic vision, and finally building &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; that translates conceptual tactics into actual, positive experiences for people—clients, customers, or constituents. When everything goes right there is also a larger shift in the organization&amp;rsquo;s offline practices to align with the digital strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Studio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2006 I have practiced design independently. It has provided me with the flexibility to work on a wide variety of projects I care about, from &lt;a href=&quot;/all/healthcaregov&quot;&gt;massive government projects&lt;/a&gt; to small community groups in my city. I regularly build ad hoc teams to deliver the full suite of design and development services and love working with great collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Areas of Interest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of ideas that I return to over and over and am eager to explore further:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big, messy challenges&lt;/strong&gt; - I&amp;rsquo;m drawn to large, complicated challenges, where an initial need is recognized, but the way forward is unknown.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context &amp;amp; connected information&lt;/strong&gt; - I&amp;rsquo;ve been intrigued with finding meaningful ways to connect information, provide greater context, and produce greater understanding for some time. Mixtrail was an attempt at this. Also see &lt;a href=&quot;/all/communicating-complexity&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/all/conversations-about-data&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increasing the reach of deep institutional knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; - This has been a theme in a number of projects such as the most recent &lt;a href=&quot;/all/terrapin-bright-green&quot;&gt;Terrapin&lt;/a&gt; work and &lt;a href=&quot;/all/stone-barns-center-for-food-agriculture&quot;&gt;Stone Barns&lt;/a&gt;, both organizations who deliver deep wisdom directly to some, but are eager to broaden the reach to much larger numbers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deep content, longform, features&lt;/strong&gt; - Finding methods and forms for presenting deep, rich information online is a very interesting issue. Some of the [ReliefWeb] work dealt with this, and the upcoming [Terrapin] work leans heavily it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Squeaky&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late 2001, Anthony Del Monte founded &lt;a href=&quot;/all/squeaky-wheel-media&quot;&gt;Squeaky Wheel Media&lt;/a&gt; and Mailet Lopez and I joined him as Partners. We had worked together at the recently defunct Vizy Interactive. I was the Creative Director. Our fledgling, NYC-based boutique agency served a variety of clients—MasterCard International, SoBe Beverages, Blue Buffalo, and others—and grew steadily through some tough New York City years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in Livonia, Michigan in a wonderful, loving family, and enjoyed all the benefits that come with such an environment. First I was a Lego kid, then I was an art kid. I studied at the excellent Cleveland Institute of Art, an historic school with an institutional appreciation for hard work and craftsmanship, and the Lacoste School of Art in Lacoste, France. In France, I met &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bdphotography.com&quot;&gt;a beautiful girl&lt;/a&gt; from New York City who loved to laugh. She put me under a trance and drew me to New York. In order to make the move possible, I started designing websites. Both the girl and the profession stuck. We now live in Jersey City, New Jersey with our amazing little girl.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conversations About Data</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/conversations-about-data</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 11:33:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/conversations-about-data</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;At times we may assume the value of specific data are self-evident, when they may not be. This misses an opportunity to expand the audience for the data beyond those already interested. People who are not deeply immersed in a subject matter community, but nonetheless could bring new ideas to the table, may benefit from some data literacy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Recently Project Open Data launched Next.Data.gov as a vision for where Data.gov might go. It does a nice job of promoting the use of government data and modelling examples of companies who have successfully used that data. The launch was accompanied by requests for feedback. I put together some thoughts on an area I think could be explored a bit: &lt;em&gt;profiling prominent data sets through conversations with subject matter experts who understand and can share the value of the data with people who may not immediately understand its value&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;An idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very simplified life cycle for government data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data is collected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data is released&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The value of the data is understood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data is used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve been good at the first step for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few years we&amp;rsquo;ve made great strides in the second step. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.data.gov&quot;&gt;Data.gov&lt;/a&gt; and related data portals provide unprecedented access to data that can be reused in innumerable ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been lots effort put into the fourth step, advocating and incentivizing for the use of government data through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthdatapalooza.org/&quot;&gt;Health Datapalooza&lt;/a&gt;, challenges, and other efforts. &lt;a href=&quot;http://next.data.gov&quot;&gt;Next.data.gov&lt;/a&gt; (and alpha.data.gov before it) does a great job of profiling successful use of data by entrepreneurs and folks in the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The third step is one that I think could use some more love.&lt;/strong&gt; Helping people to see the value in a specific data set could help start the gears turning in the minds of creative people who may not immediately understand the contents of a new release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve put together a rough concept of a &lt;em&gt;Conversation&lt;/em&gt; page for next.data.gov that would accompany prominent or undervalued data releases to provide context. These conversations are intended to help &amp;ldquo;unpack&amp;rdquo; the raw data from multiple perspectives; helping those who might use or share  the data understand the potential value in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept was also [submitted to Data.gov&amp;rsquo;s Github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example is based on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cms.gov/Research-Statistics-Data-and-Systems/Statistics-Trends-and-Reports/Medicare-Provider-Charge-Data/Inpatient.html&quot;&gt;Inpatient Medicare Provider Charge Data&lt;/a&gt;. All the copy is for demonstration purposes only. It&amp;rsquo;s based on a rough understanding of the data and is likely to be inaccurate. But hopefully it helps articulate the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container class=&quot;img-full&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img_conversations-about-data_body_01&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_conversations-about-data_body_01&quot; alt=&quot;concept diagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this concept is helpful in some way and look forward to any discussion it may provoke.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Communicating Complexity</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/communicating-complexity</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 14:15:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/communicating-complexity</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;In all our efforts creating, designing, and developing websites or other digital products, our goal should be improvement. Yes, our craftsmanship and technique. Of course, our content and tools. But more importantly, the efficacy of all this work. This article explores one approach that may help tackle one of our biggest challenges: communicating effectively about complex, confusing topics; and proposes &lt;a href=&quot;#section-5&quot;&gt;a possible remedy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;It feels like a lot is changing.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen lots of innovation in the form of best practices for planning and creating content and websites. Native and Web apps have been changing the ways we consume content for a number of years. New services and systems are reinterpreting methods and platforms for publishing. That’s all great, but I worry when the focus is more on the “how” than the “why”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Innovation should lead to progress. Disruption for disruption’s sake is just rote start-up incubator process seeking out problems to capitalize on. So if we think in broad terms about our information landscape, what needs are still unmet? What are we overlooking? As a whole, what direction is it taking us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;#section-5&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_communicating-complexity_body_01&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;#section-5&quot;&gt;Skip past the long-winded babbling and check out an example of a Big, Living Page.
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;We’re good at a lot of things…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We’re able to communicate easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We’re able to publish easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We stay updated easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We’re able to find specific things that we’re looking for easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We’re good at entertaining.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We’re good at making beautiful things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;…And not so good at others.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking about the big issues. Are we getting more knowledgeable, better informed, more well-rounded? (Of course YOU are, but what about everyone else?) Is our culture becoming a more lush and nuanced? Are we more empathetic? Are our arguments becoming more reasoned? Is fact winning out over hearsay? Do we feel more in control or less? Do we know our local and global neighbors better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all complex challenges and not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; solvable by us content, design, and development folks. But we have a role to play. We’ve made it easy to find specific things, popular things, and things we will likely like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We &lt;strong&gt;haven’t&lt;/strong&gt; made it very easy to navigate the murky water. When we find ourselves needing to investigate new topics, ideas, or circumstances, our search often falls flat. When we are first immersing ourselves into something new, we don’t know where to start, what to search for, what questions to ask, or who to turn to. This is the space where I see a lot of need to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Web, our forms and the way we use them contributes to this problem.&lt;/strong&gt; Our pages are often simplistic. There are too many of them. They rot, get duplicated, lost, or are never found to begin with. Streams become overwhelming. There is a lot of innovation going on around streams and the various ways they are created and managed. But I’d like to look at the humble ‘page’ and how it might be used to address varied, complex, blurry subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The humble Web page. The single, simple document. If we re-imagine what pages can be, might they hold the key to communicating complexity in helpful ways?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;Exciting new developments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I had huge buckets of legos. (Luckily my mom still kept them and I can soon reclaim them under the guise of toys for my daughter.) There was no better sound than dumping out those buckets onto the carpet and seeing all those components ready to be made into something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re at a similar point in time. There have been so many ideas brought to the table in the last year or so. It can be a bit overwhelming, but let’s look at some of the pieces we have at our disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;We’re producing content in more thoughtful ways.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand the reasons for and value of keeping our content and presentation separate. We’re moving toward Create Once, Publish Everywhere thinking. We know our content–and the containers it comes in–should reflect our audiences’ needs and not our organization’s structure. We understand the role of metadata and semantic markup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;We’re building our sites more wisely.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, we broke our habit of building table-based layouts using CSS. The release of CSS3 and HTML5 push this ability even further, allowing us to dynamically render live data with SVGs, animate transitions, and so much more. We have more control over our typography with Web fonts. Our browsers are better. When they are inconsistent we’ve got resets, shims, and polyfils. We’ve realized that we don’t need to start from scratch all the time. We’ve embraced frameworks, code libraries, Twitter Bootstrap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;We’re paying more attention to our users.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conduct user testing. We create scenarios and user stories. We know they are using a plethora of devices, so we’re starting use responsive design principles when it’s appropriate, and think about mobile issues early in the process. We know they are overloaded with information, and time/context-shift with Instapaper, Pocket, or Flipboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;We’re refining our process.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Websites are becoming products integral to the operation of the organizations that once thought of them as brochures. Agile development, lean start-up thinking help us work smart. We’re thinking beyond the sites we’re currently building to manage change well in the future. We’re building our products on top of our own APIs. Then we’re opening those APIs up. Our specializations have become more defined and we’re talking amongst ourselves to share experiences and best practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of all these things shows a growing sense of maturity and control. We’re responding quickly to shifting conditions, questioning the very constructs that define and limit our content. But before we pat our collective backs, there are a number of areas where our game is still sloppy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-3&quot;&gt;Looking for inspiration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Read later” services have a lot to teach us. Their approach to extracting the primary content of a page often liberates content from the doldrums of a life lived among the noise of advertisements, overblown website navigation systems, recommended content, and other clutter. These services respect the text enough to allow it to stand on its own. They value clarity, legibility, and portability. They value our textual content more than we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certainly other situations in which the presentation of the content improves its consumption and understanding. In some ways, this fights against the previously stated idea of keeping content and presentation separate. But to deny that the way information is presented does not inform it’s meaning is to discard every development in graphic design from the Book of Kells, to Gutenberg, to the Bauhaus, to David Carson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Print Mags and Product Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve dealt with similar issues before. Graphic design in print has explored this for generations. For a number of reasons, we weren’t able to take advantage of this thinking online in the past. We had to deal with bandwidth, CMS, and front-end limitations. A lot of this is changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Product pages and pages loosely referred to as having that “Web 2.0 look” have shed some of our early conservativism. They stopped worry about the fold, big photos, and finally embraced white space. This approach eschews the heatmap promoters and puts some trust back into the content and the designer’s ability to move a reader around a page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img_communicating-complexity_body_02&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_communicating-complexity_body_02&quot; alt=&quot;Examples of big pages&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A few examples of “big pages”: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/ios/ios6/&quot;&gt;Apple&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.charitywater.org/projects/d2p/&quot;&gt;Charity Water&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://37signals.com/&quot;&gt;37signals&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;http://gim.ie/PXYD&quot;&gt;View other examples&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Infographics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infographics translate data info visual form. Sometimes the density of information can be overwhelming, but the attempt to take complex information and make it understandable is helpful. Usually we encounter infographics online in image form, not programmed pages. Or when you do see dynamic graphics, the have been created to serve an ephemeral need, to support a news item or interpret some timely event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img_communicating-complexity_body_03&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_communicating-complexity_body_03&quot; alt=&quot;Examples of infographics&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A few examples of infographics: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.whitehouse.gov/infographics/extending-middle-class-tax-cuts&quot;The White House&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.good.is/infographics&quot;&gt;Good&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2012/08/05/sports/olympics/the-100-meter-dash-one-race-every-medalist-ever.html&quot;&gt;The New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These existing models are a good point of departure. They can inform what a comprehensive, engaging, consumable experience can look like. So how do we learn from these examples, employ the new developments discussed above, and put them to work to help us communicate complexity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(OK, you’re probably getting tired of my rambling. If so, jump to an &lt;a href=&quot;#section-5&quot;&gt;example of what a solution might look like&lt;/a&gt;. But you’re gonna miss the whole idea if you do.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-4&quot;&gt;Comprehensive + Frequently Updated = Big, Living Pages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply making “big pages” long and visual isn’t the point. The point is to make pages that aspire to be comprehensive while remaining user friendly, becoming a “Page of Record” for a given topic. Pages that aspire to get better over time, remain accurate and relevant, and become increasingly effective. This is admittedly hard. It requires a change in approach that favors a longer view of content than the usual ‘create, publish, forget’ process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create Once, Revise Frequently&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why don’t we edit more? When new developments occur, our instinct is usually to publish something new about the developments, rather than focusing on reviewing and reworking the existing pages we’ve already created, ensuring they are up-to-date and clear based on the new thinking. Maybe it is a carry-over from pre-digital/offline thinking where we couldn’t just jump back into an existing document and renew it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is a mistake for a number of reasons. Once again, we’re focusing on discussing the new stuff without context. Wikipedia stands alone as a site/service that takes constant refinement seriously and values it as part of what makes its content valuable. Everyone know Wikipedia pages a “alive” and always changing. They also make the revision history available, which is helpful in understanding how things have changed over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we’ve embraced editing and refining our content instead of just papering over it with new content, we can focus on keeping it fresh and improving it over time. We can study our audience and try to find out how clear, easy, and helpful our content is. We can have conversations with our audience to gauge whether or not our content is making a difference. We can spot problems and mistakes we’re making. We can identify gaps. Involving our audience makes our content more collaborative. Not necessarily in the full crowdsourced way, but it means we’re checking our work to see if it’s effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of interest in data these days–big data, open data–especially within the public sector. Frequently when organizations embrace “open data”, they start looking around for data they can release. Less frequently, but just as importantly, they look to the use and interpretation of data. Live data and APIs make it possible to display running records of data on an ongoing basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Embracing Constraints&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we attempt to utilize this approach beyond the occasional one-off page, there is a need for constraints. Given the effort involved, this is more intended for evergreen content. For this approach to work, we’d need to be realistic about the amount of work that’s involved. That includes design and development time, as well as the effort to maintaining the content and an organizational commitment to favoring quality over quantity. A site primarily handled this way would need to set limits for the number of pages that are bit off. It could be easy to slip into building something that is too much to maintain. (On this topic, The Pruitt-Igoe Myth has become a classic for building without an eye towards maintenance.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also important to understand what this sort of page will not do well. There needs to be a choice of whether the big page is going to deliver all the content within itself, or whether it will be a broad overview that directs people elsewhere for specifics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There could be a whole other discussion of the technologies used for this, but I don’t feel there are too many limitations, beyond imagination, keeping this from happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Benefits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of things that the “big, living page” approach does that our more typical methods of publishing cannot. For one, a big, living page acknowledges the true complexity of the given topic instead of presenting a false, streamlined experience. It provides an overview of the wide variety of aspects of a single topic to help the reader understand the topic as a whole, even if that understanding is somewhat shallow. It provides them with a lot of next steps, which will hopefully now be informed by greater understanding of the topic as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But talking can only get us so far. Let’s take a look at what this might feel like.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-5&quot;&gt;An Example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following example is intended to present a model for how a broad, confusing topic could be presented to an audience that doesn’t quite know where to begin. The example uses the intentionally silly topic of a government page about dogs in order to abstract the content within. This concept was originally developed for the Presidential Innovation Fellows MyGov team, who are embarking on an effort to “rapidly prototype a streamlined and intuitive system for presenting information and accepting feedback around the needs of citizens”. In an effort to be helpful, and giving in to a tendency to stick my nose where it doesn’t belong, I put this together to define “big, living page” thinking. This was created outside of the official MyGov process, so it’s purely theoretical and does not reflect their activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-full&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img_communicating-complexity_body_04&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_communicating-complexity_body_04&quot; alt=&quot;Diagram explaining big, living pages&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said at the outset, this is about learning how to tell really complex stories in meaningful ways. This is a start. I’m interested in hearing what you think. Help evolve this idea and move us forward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Reasons to Be a Presidential Innovation Fellow</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/five-reasons-to-be-a-presidential-innovation-fellow</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 15:25:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/five-reasons-to-be-a-presidential-innovation-fellow</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;On May 23, US CTO Todd Park and CIO Steven VanRoekel announced a new program called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.whitehouse.gov/innovationfellows&quot;&gt;Presidential Innovation Fellows&lt;/a&gt;. Park explains the &amp;ldquo;new initiative will bring top innovators from outside government for focused &amp;lsquo;tours of duty&amp;rsquo; with our best federal innovators on game-changing projects. Combining the know-how of citizen change agents and government change agents in small, agile teams that move at high speed, these projects aim to deliver significant results within six months.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;This piece was &lt;a href=&quot;http://techpresident.com/news/22308/backchannel-ed-mullen-five-reasons-be-presidential-innovation-fellow&quot;&gt;originally published on techPresident&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is a new program, I went through a &lt;a href=&quot;http://makinggood.edmullen.com/index.php/article/how_i_became_involved_with_healthcare_gov/&quot;&gt;similar experience&lt;/a&gt; two years ago when I joined the Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) for a “tour” leading design on Healthcare.gov. It was an amazing experience for me, and I hope everyone in the tech / design / content / data / Web world recognizes the massive opportunity this program represents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what makes it such a great opportunity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the right size.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way many of us work in this field, we are either independent operators or jump between clients, companies, agencies, or start-ups at a greater frequency than people in other areas. This is at odds with the way the government operates where hiring takes a long time. The six-month duration of the program fits well within this reality. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to put the demands of day-to-day life on hold for six months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work with the HealthCare.gov team lasted about five months. It was a massive team lift by people across skill sets. Everyone worked extremely hard. There were a couple weeks I was putting in upwards of nineteen-hour days. That’s not a pace that can be sustained for long, but I loved doing it because the work was important. Six months is short enough to make the sprint manageable, and long enough time to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;You will work with amazing people.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people you will work with will challenge and inspire you in ways you can&amp;rsquo;t imagine. As Todd Park has said, government folks are among the most mission-oriented people you will meet. They are there because they want to do important things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to work closely with Todd, White House Director of Digital Strategy Macon Phillips, and a number of super-smart individuals from HHS during my time in DC. These people forced me to think in new ways and consider things I wouldn’t normally have thought about. Without a doubt, there is no other incubator, mentorship, bootcamp, start-up, or other experience-building opportunity I would choose over working with those people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;You will gain as much as you give.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The private sector often affords us with opportunities to take chances, experiment, and fail in ways that would be unacceptable with taxpayers&amp;#39; money. The downside of those risks can be big, but so can the upsides. Either way, those lessons are extremely valuable and provide great perspective. These fellowships provide private sector folks a great opportunity to bring some of that experience to bear on big, government challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cross-pollination works in both directions. Public sector folks benefit from working within a system that is focused on service not selling. In my experience at HHS, that meant greater focus on accessibility, user testing, clarity, and attention to the fringe cases that are easy to dismiss when you are focused on pushing product. There are not many opportunities to shift smoothly between public and private contexts; yet doing so was very informative to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;You will be of service to your country.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are lucky in our regular work lives, the work we do provides us with a sense of accomplishment and meaning. I&amp;rsquo;ve had the good fortune of working with a lot of clients who are doing good work in the world. However, working directly in impactful ways for your country is a different thing all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As designers, developers, or specialists of whatever kind, the contributions we make can&amp;rsquo;t compare to those of the men and women in the armed forces who leave their families, put their lives on the line, serve, and carry the weight that service sometimes brings. Yet, through the specialized skills and expertise that we have, we can play a role. We can be a part of making our country stronger, smarter, and of better service to the public. All political ideologies want our government to be efficient and go about its business in productive, effective ways. This is your chance to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;It will be hard…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, you’ll be in DC during August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very nature of the Fellows program is to bring in disruptive personalities and ideas. The scale of the systems and information is massive. There are entrenched systems, policies, and procedures. Disruption is not always a welcome condition. And disruption that is not sustainable beyond the timeframe of the program isn’t helpful. The challenge will be to deliver solutions that can ‘catch’, becoming useful tools, approaches, models, ideas, systems, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will certainly be stretched to the limits of your abilities. To a large degree, you’re jumping in without knowing what you’re getting into. There will probably be some awkward moments as you and your collaborators get to know each other and the different things you each bring to the table. Be flexible. Identify what needs to be done and do it. In time the team will gel and you’ll be off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;…But it will change your life.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not being hyperbolic. You will do deeply meaningful work. You will work with truly inspiring people. And you will become significantly better at whatever it is you do. You’ll step up your game. My time working on HealthCare.gov was truly life changing. The opportunity that is being made available through the Presidential Innovation Fellows is remarkable. You should request an application right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;quiet&quot;&gt;Photo CC BY-SA 2.0 by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/hbarrison/6843914174/sizes/l/&quot;&gt;Harvey Barrison&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One World Youth Project</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/one-world-youth-project</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 15:21:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/one-world-youth-project</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Working toward a just world built through the actions of empowered, discerning and empathetic generations of global citizens, One World Youth Project links schools globally in service-learning to prepare the next generation for the globalized 21st century. Their concern is that our youth don’t have the global life skills needed to thrive in our increasingly interconnected society and economy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buscada.com&quot;&gt;Kaushik Panchal&lt;/a&gt; to help One World Youth Project in a variety of ways. Initial activities included the creation of materials to aid in fundraising. From there a new website was launched which focused on clearly explaining their offerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexslider flexslider-full&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_one-world-youth-project_body_01.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;One World Youth Project Website&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_one-world-youth-project_body_02.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_one-world-youth-project_body_03.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_one-world-youth-project_body_04.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Editorial content focuses on exposing program activities and broader evolving global education issues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_one-world-youth-project_body_05.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_one-world-youth-project_body_06.jpg&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;flex-caption&quot;&gt;Content strategy was a major of the OWYP collaboration included extensive training on social media practice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through research and reassessment, the partnership worked to help strengthen OWYP and help them work toward their mission of a just world built through the actions of empowered, discerning and empathetic generations of global citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Clearly articulate what OWYP does and believes.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One World Youth Project is a complicated organization to explain. They are a youth run group with very big ideas and aspirations. The ideas behind what they do are wise and intentional. Their worldview is vast. On an inspirational level, there is a lot there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The services they offer are also very complex. They work on two levels, through college “Hubs”, which are their actual customers, and within middle and high school classrooms, where college students facilitate inter-classroom cultural exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked with OWYP to define core messaging and package those messages for public dissemination and private use in fundraising activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Establish good practices for internal communication, outbound messaging, and ongoing public conversation.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a series of editorial meetings and content assessment, the team established strong practices for publishing content and engaging their community. Understanding the appropriate channels for various activities led to clearer communication of core values and offerings, as well as building bonds with the larger community working on similar issues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting to Know Each Other, 7000 Miles Away</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/getting-to-know-each-other-7000-miles-away</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 15:58:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/getting-to-know-each-other-7000-miles-away</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Not long before Lake Area Middle School was destroyed by Hurricane Katrina, &lt;a href=&quot;http://oneworldyouthproject.org/about-the-organization/board-2/jess-rimington/&quot;&gt;Jess Rimington&lt;/a&gt; was facilitating a classroom exchange program there; one of the earliest implementations of her then-fledgling organization, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oneworldyouthproject.org/&quot;&gt;One World Youth Project&lt;/a&gt;. Jess’s classroom was paired with a classroom in Ulan Bator, Mongolia. Over the course of the academic year, the students in her New Orleans classroom and their Mongolian counterparts shared their experiences, stories, and learned the similarities of their lives. They got to know each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the floodwalls were breached, the Gentilly was flooded and with it, Lake Area Middle School. Jess heard nothing from her New Orleanian students. It would be months before she would hear the harrowing stories of students waving down planes from their rooftops or hear about the boy who was forced to break through his ceiling to get free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the students in Ulan Bator that she heard from. They were worried about their friends. They had heard about the storm and seen pictures. They set out to help. The students raised a few hundred US dollars—a lot of money in Ulan Bator—and collected and sent clothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why? Because they knew the students in New Orleans. Their lives had intersected and a hurricane 7000 miles away had come ashore in their own lives.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jess founded One World Youth Project eight years ago as a high school student. She’d had the opportunity to travel to South Africa and experience the life-changing shift that occurs when you are able to step out of your own context and see it relative to the very different and very similar lives of people in other contexts. But she knew this was not an opportunity most people get to experience. Out of this realization, OWYP was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the eight years since it’s founding, One World Youth Project has connected students in 67 schools in 26 countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One World Youth Projects develops global citizenship skills by establishing OWYP “Hubs” at universities around the world. University students are trained in the curriculum and program methodology. These “project ambassadors” are then assigned to local middle or high school classrooms, where they facilitate a cultural exchange program with students in another classroom somewhere else in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the eight years since it’s founding, One World Youth Project has connected students in 67 schools in 26 countries, most recently focusing on Washington D.C. and Prishtina, Kosovo. This coming year they will expand to Islamabad, Istanbul and Georgetown in Guyana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, OWYP hosted a reception here in New York City. Several of their painfully young and smart staff shared stories. Surya Kundu spoke of the challenges she had as a Teach for America corp member in Chicago with students entirely unfamiliar with her Indian heritage. Ossob Mohamud spoke of her experience in a OWYP classroom in Qatar, discussing women’s rights with students, some of whom questioned whether the idea was inherently Western. Cady Voge expressed that “once you know someone’s story, it is impossible to hate them.” Jess told the story of the Ulan Bator / New Orleans connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their experiences have proven to them the importance of building a skillset that increases student capacity to see themselves in one another, while developing the ability to communicate cross-culturally and work together effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had the pleasure of working with Jess and team for about two years—along with my colleague &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buscada.com/&quot;&gt;Kaushik Panchal&lt;/a&gt;—to help the group communicate online and develop some of the tools they need to do their important work. In my work life, I have tried to focus my energy as much as possible in supporting organizations who are doing good work in the world. OWYP meets this criteria in every way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no doubt whatsoever that their successes are just beginning. Please take some time to learn more about them. Not long from now we will speak about them in the way we speak about Teach for America today. That’s where they are headed. They have no small plans. I just thought you’d like to know now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make Your Own Rules</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/make-your-own-rules</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2011 14:52:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/make-your-own-rules</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I walk to work, I often have ideas as my mind wanders. This is one of those. It was sparks by thinking of the sentencing of Rod Blagojevich, marijuana possessions, and crimes committed by financial institutions during the financial crisis. When you compare sentences, the magnitude of the crime and its impact on society often seem disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also true with government spending and taxes. The actual “settings” often don’t match what we think the should be. We are also usually unclear as to what the settings are at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img_make-your-own-rules_body_01&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_make-your-own-rules_body_01&quot; alt=&quot;Step 1 diagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this idea would be to A) clarify what we feel is most important B) see how that matches with reality and C) develop a sense of where our priorities should go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img_make-your-own-rules_body_02&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_make-your-own-rules_body_02&quot; alt=&quot;Step 2 diagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have the time to take this any further, but here’s what I mocked up as a possible Web tool to accomplish this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on the Recent #dotgov Dialogue</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/thoughts-on-the-recent-dotgov-dialogue</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2011 16:44:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/thoughts-on-the-recent-dotgov-dialogue</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Recently the General Services Administration conducted &lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/&quot;&gt;an open, public dialogue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to solicit ideas about how the government could improve Federal .gov websites. The dialogue was conducted online using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ideascale.com&quot;&gt;IdeaScale&lt;/a&gt; platform and will be archived for future review. I’ve compiled my thoughts on the dialogue for the GSA team. It’s long, but I want to give as much feedback as I can.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Dialogue Catalyst&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was &lt;a href=&quot;http://makinggood.edmullen.com/index.php/article/national_dialogue/&quot; title=&quot;asked to participate&quot;&gt;asked to participate&lt;/a&gt; as a “dialogue catalyst”. The GSA folks didn’t set down specific requirements and allowed me and the other dozen or so catalysts to determine how best they could participate. Some catalysts felt their most valuable role was in lending their unique subject matter expertise to the discussion. This made a lot of sense for the people who have very deep knowledge within a specialization. I felt the way I could be most helpful was in encouraging discussion around posted ideas, bringing in ideas that I see outside the dialogue into the discussion, and reaching out to experts whose input would make the discussion richer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Quality of Submissions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, I found the quality of suggestions was very high. The discussion around submitted ideas also usually helped to fill out the original submission. Across the board, ideas seemed to be coming from people who “knew what they were talking about” and who have thought deeply about the issues outside of the dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Participation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just over two weeks, 436 ideas were submitted and 996 people participated in the discussion, either by submitting ideas or commenting on existing ideas. I heard some feedback that the fact users had to register to participate was a disincentive to participate, but my feeling is that it kept the quality of discussion high and clean. (You could register without identifying yourself.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the people who participated appeared to either be government folks, or people who might be considered near-government: either good government advocates or people who encourage government to address certain issues. This makes perfect sense, although I would have liked to see more people who are Web practitioners from across the private sector offer up lessons from their work. This is harder to do, and something that would be worth trying to figure out for future efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there was a strong tendency towards practices that are thoughtful, measured, research-based, and done “the right way”. Generally, this sounds great. We want the government to practice in a responsible, considered way. But outside of government, this isn’t always the case. So what’s the problem? I feel weird saying this, but sometimes there are situations where the best thing you can do is “just get it done” and put it out into the world. In the world of startups, there is a lot of discussion now about Lean thinking; that if you wait until your product is fully ready, you waited too long. So I’m not advocating for bad practices, I’m just saying that voice, for good or bad, wasn’t really present in the discussion, but it definitely exists outside of government decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Final Report&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final report is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usa.gov/webreform/national-dialogue-report.pdf&quot;&gt;available for download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;Important General Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Big vs. Little, One vs. Many&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One theme that emerged across many ideas was the issue of whether the government should focus on delivering services through fewer, or possibly one central website (see &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Follow-UK-s-Directgov-Model/82008-4097&quot; title=&quot;Follow UK's Directgov Model&quot;&gt;Follow UK&amp;#8217;s Directgov Model&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221;), or whether it should focus on more, topic/audience-specific websites (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buscada.com&quot; title=&quot;Kaushik Panchal&quot;&gt;Kaushik Panchal&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Use-the-network/81991-4097&quot; title=&quot;Use the Network&quot;&gt;Use the Network&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221;). As with most things, both is probably the answer. To me, the best approach is probably to encourage practices that allow content to be found and shared easily across platforms: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply proper metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use semantic marked up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure easy discovery via search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Properly archive outdated or ephemeral content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do whatever needs to be done to put content and services at hands-reach for 311-type services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Differentiate-between-ephemeral-and-evergreen-content/81932-4097&quot; title=&quot;Differentiate between ephemeral and evergreen content&quot;&gt;Differentiate between ephemeral and evergreen content&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an issue that I think about a lot and which I see done wrong all the time. Content is not all created for the same purpose. Some content serves a short-term purpose and some is more timely and ephemeral. This is not just an issue of old vs. new content. Being conscious of the purpose and appropriate channel for the content is important. Generating content is easy. Managing a large collection of knowledge and up-to-date, relevant content is hard. Which leads to&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Content Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/halvorson&quot; title=&quot;Kristina Halvorson&quot;&gt;Kristina Halvorson&lt;/a&gt; recommended &lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Create-a-federal-website-content-strategy/82890-4097&quot; title=&quot;creating a federal website content strategy&quot;&gt;creating a federal website content strategy&lt;/a&gt;. Other people submitted ideas along the same track. The point of the theme is that you should think ahead about the substance, function, need, audience, governance, and maintenance of the content you produce. This is often at odds with the last minute push to “get something out” about an upcoming event or marketing push. It’s important to recognize the needs of those who are marketing the efforts of an agency, but they need to be balanced with the needs of those within the agency or department who need to serve the ongoing content needs of their audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Better promotion of existing .gov services&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many times during the dialogue you heard people stating that the Feds should do this or that, followed by the Fed folks humbly stating something like “you can similar service here”. The takeaway is that there is a ton of great work already being done by the various Web teams that people don’t know about. Somehow more effort should be made to let the public know about these things, or increase their visibility. Some things, such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://search.usa.gov&quot; title=&quot;search.usa.gov&quot;&gt;search.usa.gov&lt;/a&gt; are great tools, but could potentially be &lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/All-Gov-sites-should-use-search.usa.gov-to-power-site-search/83099-4097&quot; title=&quot;tweaked in ways to make them more useful or more visible&quot;&gt;tweaked in ways to make them more useful or more visible&lt;/a&gt;. This mirrors my personal belief that one challenge for government is that when it does things well, it doesn’t get credit because those efforts become invisible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Usability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of talk of usability. i agree, but you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/ideafactory.do?id=4097&amp;amp;mode=member&amp;amp;discussionFilter=byids&amp;amp;discussionID=11752&quot; title=&quot;read the usability stuff here&quot;&gt;read the usability stuff here&lt;/a&gt;. Be sure to read &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/AaronGustafson&quot; title=&quot;Aaron Gustafson&quot;&gt;Aaron Gustafson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/pmd/148930-4097&quot; title=&quot;Optimize user paths&quot;&gt;Optimize user paths&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Open Analytics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dmitry Kachaev recommended &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Open-Web-Analytics-for-EVERY-.gov-website/81974-4097&quot; title=&quot;open Web analytics for all .gov websites&quot;&gt;open Web analytics for all .gov websites&lt;/a&gt;. This is an interesting idea. It would allow the public to crunch numbers in an interesting way. I think it would encourage content creators, who don’t always have access to analytics about the content they create, to take better care of existing content. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-3&quot;&gt;Important Social Media Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was asked to pay specific attention to the Social Media space. Ideas from this discussion that I find important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Use existing and open source tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a theme I liked that focused on using existing tools, frequently open source, often with established users and cultures. It makes sense from an economic standpoint, but even more because these tools reflect iterative lessons learned about what works. Some known areas of concern for the .gov context involve accessibility and Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) considerations. See: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/danlatorre&quot; title=&quot;Dan Latorre&quot;&gt;Dan Latorre&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Encourage-use-of-popular--OpenSource-platforms/82401-4097&quot; title=&quot;Encourage use of popular #OpenSource platforms&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Encourage use of popular #OpenSource platforms&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Do-Not-Replicate-Social-Media/82067-4097&quot; title=&quot;Do Not Replicate Social Media&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Do Not Replicate Social Media&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Have-a-Gov-Wide-Team-that-Evaluates--Presents-and-PurchasesTools/82626-4097&quot; title=&quot;Have a Gov-Wide Team that Evaluates, Presents and PurchasesTools&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Have a Gov-Wide Team that Evaluates, Presents and PurchasesTools&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Allow Feds to communicate with citizens via social media&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea to &lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Support-Employee-Access-to-Web-2.0-Sites/82289-4097&quot; title=&quot;Support Employee Access to Web 2.0 Sites&quot;&gt;Support Employee Access to Web 2.0 Sites&lt;/a&gt; was raised. I agree, though it does raise some issues of workload, loosening control of message, and culture shifts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Plan for effective use of social media in disasters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I posted the idea &lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Institute-Effective-Social-Media-Emergency-Plans/82615-4097&quot; title=&quot;Institute Effective Social Media Emergency Plans&quot;&gt;Institute Effective Social Media Emergency Plans&lt;/a&gt;. Many gov teams already probably do this, but what may not be as considered is the content strategy for producing resources, materials and content ahead of time that can prove effective in times of crisis, and pushing those materials out as soon as disasters strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tension over “get the basics done” vs “be where the people are”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not an idea in itself, I wanted to call attention to the difference of opinion between those who feel .gov teams should do the basics first (read: create effective websites”) before embracing additional responsibilities such as engaging on a variety of social media platforms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-4&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Requirements, Guidence, Incentives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reading through the ideas, you read a lot of “require all .gov websites to&amp;#8230;” or “all .gov websites should&amp;#8230;” statements in connection with thoughtful ideas. (Ex: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/All-Gov-sites-should-use-search.usa.gov-to-power-site-search/83099-4097&quot; title=&quot;All Gov sites should use search.usa.gov to power site search&quot;&gt;All Gov sites should use search.usa.gov to power site search&lt;/a&gt;” or “&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/a/dtd/Make-usability-testing-and-508-testing-required-PRIOR-to-launch/81928-4097&quot; title=&quot;Make usability testing and 508 testing required PRIOR to launch&quot;&gt;Make usability testing and 508 testing required PRIOR to launch&lt;/a&gt;”) In considering the validity of an idea, I think it is wise to consider the requirement aspect separately from the idea aspect. Establishing requirements for some perfectly good ideas could create inflexibility or “box checking” that would work against creative problem solving. Some things should be required. Some should be encouraged. Some should be incentivized. Some should be nudged. My guess is that the require/encourage issue closely mirrors the submitters’ views of the role of government in general. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Summarizing concepts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step for the GSA team will be to ingest all the ideas that have been submitted. They have said that they will in some way report on lessons learned from the dialogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Ratings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be good for the team to take the user submitted ratings with a grain of salt, especially on the lower and middle end. I think it’s safe to say the really highly rated ideas deserve their ratings, but when it comes to the ideas that were submitted in the second half of the dialogue, they are handicapped by two things. As more and more ideas were submitted, it became harder to get a sense of the full breadth of ideas submitted and you started to see some fragmentation and related ideas being discussed under different posts. Also time wasn’t on the side of late submissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Themes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it was &lt;a href=&quot;http://candioncontent.blogspot.com/&quot; title=&quot;Candi Harrison&quot;&gt;Candi Harrison&lt;/a&gt; who recommended that a summary of the dialogue could be gathered into maybe a dozen themes. I’d second this approach. I do think themes emerged, and a good summary would look for those themes and then cite key ideas and comments from within those themes, which I think don’t necessary align with the pre-defined campaigns set up in the IdeaScale system. The themes may be along the lines of “Process Issues: Activities that ensure a consumer/citizen focus”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tag IdeaScale&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also recommend the GSA teams add/edit some of the tags associated with the ideas into a useful taxonomy that could aid in the consumption of the ideas in tandem with the summary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Potential future structure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the IdeaScale platform succeeded in it’s core function of collecting ideas from the public and allowing for some discussion of those ideas. I don’t see any reason not to use this or a similar platform again in the future. But there may be ways to make the process even more successful. Here’s one approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of keeping all topics open the entire time, it may be helpful to have a series of focused sessions (usability, search, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Possibly 3 or 4 days in duration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Market each session to the main websites, experts, or organizations of that specialization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have dialogue catalysts with a somewhat more focused role of nurturing discussion, asking follow-up questions, seeding topics, and drawing in important voices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have an additional role for high profile subject matter experts whose task is to use his or her social reach to drum up activity and who would be the main participant of&amp;#8230;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A live, webinar/web chat/audio discussion that would happen half way through the session. The public could log in and listen to/ask questions of the expert related to the ideas that have been submitted. The expert could select some of the ideas he or she finds more important for further discussion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The dialogue catalyst could be the moderator for the live chat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-5&quot;&gt;Thanks!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really pleased to be a part of the dialogue. I hope these comments help, and I apologize for the length.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Dialogue on Improving Federal Websites</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/national-dialogue-on-improving-federal-websites</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2011 17:32:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/national-dialogue-on-improving-federal-websites</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;The Federal government is asking for your input and guidance. They are seeking input from the public, in particular those professionals who have deep know on the various aspects of content, search, usability, accessibility, social media, multilingual content, and online services.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_national-dialogue_body_01&quot; alt=&quot;banner&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Dialogue on Improving Federal Websites is a two-week online discussion of how the Federal government can better deliver information and services online. &lt;b&gt;The dialogue will launch Monday, Sept. 19 at 2 pm ET and run until Friday, Sept. 30.&lt;/b&gt;&amp;nbsp; You&amp;#8217;ll be able to access it at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/&quot; title=&quot;web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/&quot;&gt;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Please join in the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be participating as a &amp;#8220;dialogue catalyst&amp;#8221; to help keep the conversation moving. I&amp;#8217;ll be trying to connect ideas and ask good questions; draw people into the conversation who may not already be in it. I&amp;#8217;d appreciate if you do the same. Join in. Share what you&amp;#8217;ve learned. And if you think particular people would add to the conversation, reach out and ask or &lt;a href=&quot;http://makinggood.edmullen.com/index.php/contact.html/&quot; title=&quot;contact me&quot;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt; and I will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also follow comments about the dialogue on Twitter using the hashtag &lt;em&gt;#dotgov&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://craigconnects.org/2011/09/need-your-ideas-regarding-serious-improvements-to-fed-web-sites.html&quot; title=&quot;As Craig Newmark puts it&quot;&gt;As Craig Newmark puts it&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;#8220;the deal is that Fed workers are seriously interested in better customer service, etc, via their web ops. I&amp;#8217;ve worked with these folks for years, they&amp;#8217;re the real deal, and are really listening.&amp;#8221; I agree. In my experience working with Federal employees on HealthCare.gov and in other capacities, I&amp;#8217;ve been impressed time and again with their intense commitment and drive to serve the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, diversity improves all things, especially ideas. Those of us who work on Internet-related things all practice differently. We all do things in ways that we have found better for one reason or another. That&amp;#8217;s what they want to learn. Upload your wisdom so that we can all learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And please, let&amp;#8217;s keep this positive. We&amp;#8217;re citizens and our government is asking us for advice. Isn&amp;#8217;t that how it&amp;#8217;s supposed to be? &lt;a href=&quot;http://candioncontent.blogspot.com/2011/09/join-us-for-national-discussion-on.html&quot; title=&quot;Candi Harrison warns&quot;&gt;Candi Harrison warns&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;#8220;whiners aren’t allowed to play.&amp;nbsp; This isn’t a gripe session.&amp;nbsp; This is a chance to float your ideas and join citizens, colleagues, advocates, authorities, and others in thrashing out ways the government can improve customer service through the web.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll see you at &lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/&quot; title=&quot;web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/&quot;&gt;http://web-reform-dialogue.ideascale.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attack Big Problems</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/attack-big-problems</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2011 10:03:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/attack-big-problems</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;When you have a worldview that looks to solve the big, underlying issues, you start with the problem and seek the solution that will fix it. Too often I feel like those of us developing Internet-related products or businesses are not thinking big enough; aren’t moving us ahead in really consequential ways.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;This originally was a cross-post to the MixTrail blog. MixTrail is a new startup that Robb Smylie and I are developing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re developing a business, it is of course important to find “product/market fit”. If someone’s investing money in your company, they don’t want to think you’re on some meandering expedition to just make some stuff. But simply finding a market and figuring out something to put in front of them is, well, kind of boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last ten years, my MixTrail partner Robb Smylie has been helping Teach for America solve their big challenge: to educate children in low-income, underserved communities. That’s a big problem. He’s done this by leveraging technology in a way that makes the impact of the organization scale up efficiently. The more work that can be automated through algorithms, or eliminated by making data more usable, the more that can be done with fewer resources. Technology can have a huge impact on how people do their jobs when applied thoughtfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own design practice, I have tried to work with and accelerate the efforts of clients that were doing good work in the world. Whether it was designing the site that allows all Americans to find the private and public health insurance options available to them, my work with colleges helping current and prospective students know what educational options their schools offer, or helping a youth-run organization articulate it’s mission of developing young people’s global citizenship skills to investors and partners, I always try to work with people who were working towards big things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, I spent many years working on projects that were interesting and challenging, but that didn’t quite get at the big issues. They pushed product or told a good story, but they largely left the world alone. I know that experience well. But I work towards more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MixTrail is working to solve a big problem. Despite, or perhaps because of, the Internet’s low barrier for publishing information, we are not necessarily more knowledgable, deeper thinkers. As a whole, we don’t have a better handle on complex issues. In many cases, the reality is obscured by a lot of fluff and news. We’re likely to hear the latest news, but not be able to contextualize that information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MixTrail’s not going to entirely solve this problem, but it’s the space we’re working in. Bit by bit, we’re trying to create a system that will allow you to connect ideas and content in ways that makes it easy for you to gain background, context and peripheral ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got a lot of work to do, but we’re excited and working hard to make it great. More in time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do What You’re Paid For, Then Do Some More</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/do-what-youre-paid-for-then-do-some-more</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2011 10:18:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/do-what-youre-paid-for-then-do-some-more</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;If I look back at my career so far, one of the things that has been most helpful is my seeming inability to stick to the scope of the project at hand.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t mean I’m a pushover when I’m prodded to deliver more than originally agreed upon. It means I pretty much always stick my nose where I haven’t been asked. Not forcefully, of course. Just out of inquisitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know those moments, don’t you? When you feel that the thing that needs to be done isn’t exactly what you’ve been asked to do. It’s a bit beyond that. It’s the thing that others think isn’t really necessary. But you know, if you just did it, they’d see it’s value and it will make everything better. You can always just skip it, but sometimes it’s an opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be an opportunity to practice an aspect of your craft that you are still trying to figure out, or gain experience in. In the work I do, there are many invisible or behind-the-scenes things that clients often don’t know they need. It’s a great chance to work through it, develop your skills in the area, and create examples of real-world work that can help you get paid for similar work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;At Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure this is true is most work scenarios, but most of my work is consulting with clients. Here are two examples of how this has played out for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Free People&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free People is a long time client of mine. Together we’ve redesigned their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmullen.com/work/freepeople-retail2.shtml&quot; title=&quot;e-commerce site&quot;&gt;e-commerce site&lt;/a&gt; (a few times), created a mobile store, launched several new feature sets and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmullen.com/work/freepeople-wholesale.shtml&quot; title=&quot;wholesale e-commerce store&quot;&gt;wholesale e-commerce store&lt;/a&gt;. It’s an ongoing relationship that has grown and changed over the years. (All development has been by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.weblinc.com/&quot; title=&quot;Weblinc&quot;&gt;Weblinc&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_do-what-youre-paid-for_body_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blanche website graphic&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carrieyotter.com/&quot; title=&quot;Carrie Yotter&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Carrie Yotter&lt;/a&gt; saw the &lt;a href=&quot;http://edmullen.com/work/blanche.shtml&quot; title=&quot;site I designed&quot;&gt;site I designed&lt;/a&gt; for the band Blanche many years ago. She thought there was an aesthetic affinity with what Free People was about. There was. The tactility and sense of history fit well with the Free People sensibility. The earliest work I did with them focused on telling the aesthetic story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_do-what-youre-paid-for_body_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Free People website graphic showing style&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time the project was complete, Free People knew I approach problems from as broad a perspective as I can. When they decided to foregoe new physical wholesale showrooms in favor of an online wholesale site, I was brought in again. Much of the information architecture and user experience work was not explicitly called for in the original agreement, but it was clear that it needed to be done to get it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_do-what-youre-paid-for_body_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Free People wireframe graphic&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We needed to think through the way wholesale buyers shop showrooms and how that experience and mindset could be translated in an e-commerce experience. We spent far more time on wireframes than planned, but it showed the value of the process and cut down on fiddling with designs later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_do-what-youre-paid-for_body_04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Free People wholesale website graphic&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit later, when FreePeople.com was ready for another full scale redesign, the design efforts focused entirely on creating a cutting edge store with a structure that would allow Free People&amp;#8217;s super-creative internal design team to regularly and easily reskin the site along with their marketing campaigns. The resulting site still pushes the limits from creative and technological perspectives, all while being appropriate for their unique audience. It was &amp;#8220;Responsive Web Design&amp;#8221; before there was such a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_do-what-youre-paid-for_body_05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Free People reskin project graphic&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while the original motivation for approaching me was because of certain aesthetic affinities, the reason I&amp;#8217;ve been asked back again and again is because of an entirely different skill set that I proved I had along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More info on Free People work:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmullen.com/work/freepeople-retail2.shtml&quot; title=&quot;Free People Retail Redesign&quot;&gt;Free People Retail Redesign&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp; |&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmullen.com/work/freepeople-wholesale.shtml&quot; title=&quot;Free People Wholesale site design&quot;&gt;Free People Wholesale site design&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp; |&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmullen.com/work/freepeople.shtml&quot; title=&quot;Other Free People projects&quot;&gt;Other Free People projects&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Oberlin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another (shorter) example is &lt;a href=&quot;http://edmullen.com/work/oberlin.shtml&quot; title=&quot;full global website&quot;&gt;Oberlin College&lt;/a&gt;. The college was undergoing a large scale branding overhaul that spanned more than a year. While the larger effort was under way, they asked for some help creating an interim Admissions site. The designs were well received. When the branding project wasn&amp;#8217;t, they commissioned me to take a stab at designing the homepage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_do-what-youre-paid-for_body_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Oberlin College website graphic&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design that was delivered wasn&amp;#8217;t just a graphic arrangement of elements. It foreshadowed the extended site experience, and also dealt with some difficult issues they faced; namely a branding campaign in which they were deeply invested (but wasn&amp;#8217;t well loved), and the organizational challenge of being two schools in one, the College of Arts &amp;amp; Sciences and the Conservatory of Music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_do-what-youre-paid-for_body_07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Oberlin College website graphic&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That design seemed to strike the right could with all the interested parties, and I was asked to take over the redesign of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://edmullen.com/work/oberlin.shtml&quot; title=&quot;full global website&quot;&gt;full global website&lt;/a&gt;. This work subsequently led to other higher education work for &lt;a href=&quot;http://edmullen.com/work/columbusstate.shtml&quot; title=&quot;Columbus State&quot;&gt;Columbus State&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://edmullen.com/work/siwj.shtml&quot; title=&quot;GWU&quot;&gt;GWU&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://edmullen.com/work/stockton.shtml&quot; title=&quot;Stockton&quot;&gt;Stockton&lt;/a&gt; and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More info on Oberlin College work:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmullen.com/work/oberlin.shtml&quot; title=&quot;Oberlin College Website Redesign&quot;&gt;Oberlin College Website Redesign&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;Work Outside of Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using your &amp;#8220;work skills&amp;#8221; outside of the workplace is another great opportunity. Contributing your most valuable skills to help community groups or advance social issues you care about frees you from many of the constraints of paid work. You can often approach problems in ways that business often prevents. The work you do in a volunteer capacity is just a usable in exhibiting your skills for future employment. Take it as an opportunity to do it the right way, document you work, and take it seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, extracurricular work has been very important in my career. I&amp;#8217;ve written about &lt;a href=&quot;how_i_became_involved_with_healthcare_gov/&quot; title=&quot;my work on HealthCare.gov&quot;&gt;my work on HealthCare.gov&lt;/a&gt; already, so I won&amp;#8217;t go into it here. Also, I plan to write soon about the work I did for Blanche and all the projects it led to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;Conclusion (finally)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of opportunities to do the work you&amp;#8217;re interested in. If you can&amp;#8217;t figure out how to get paid for it yet, do it anyway and use the experience and output to prove you can do the job. That work, because you care about it, will be your best work. It&amp;#8217;ll be the best projection of where you want to go and will help others see you in that light.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I Became Involved with Healthcare.gov</title>
      <link>http://edmullen.com/all/how-i-became-involved-with-healthcaregov</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 10:47:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>Edward Mullen</author>
      <guid>http://edmullen.com/all/how-i-became-involved-with-healthcaregov</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Last summer, I was asked to join the Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) team that was going to be building out HealthCare.gov—one of the earliest requirements of the Affordable Care Act—as Design Lead. How this came to be is pretty amazing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_how-i-became-involved_body_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration showing an idea&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late January of 2010, I was walking to my office, stewing about something I had been listening to on the radio before I left home about the proposed Health Reform bill. At the time, there was still a question over whether or not it would be supported by those on the left advocating for a public option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the public option was far less significant than the most important part: the establishment of the Health Insurance Exchanges. It seemed that because the idea of the Exchanges was fairly abstract, people were just skipping over it; not recognizing its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As a designer,&lt;/strong&gt; I could see what they could be. How they could be used. It seemed to make so much sense! This is one of the key roles of the designer: &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Make Visible the Future&lt;/a&gt;. So I set about to it. I spent a couple days working through concepts. &lt;strong&gt;When I finished, I published &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Envisioning a Health Insurance Exchange&lt;/a&gt; on this site.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img-container img-column&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://makinggood.edmullen.com/index.php/article/health_insurance_exchange/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img_how-i-became-involved_body_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;concept graphic&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to publishing it here, I sent a simple &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/macon44&quot;&gt;@macon44&lt;/a&gt; Twitter mention of the post to White House Director of New Media Macon Phillips. The account was very new and he didn’t have a ton of followers yet, so I thought it was a relatively less congested channel to try. (No longer the case.) I didn’t hear back, but it got through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Four months later I got an email from someone helping to bring together the team to develop HealthCare.gov asking to talk.&lt;/strong&gt; After a couple of calls with Macon and HHS CTO Todd Park, who was heading up the project from within HHS, I was asked if I wanted to come down to DC to try to bring to life some of the ideas I had talked about. Two weeks after that first email, I was in the trenches working with the full team of subject matter experts, regulators, technologists, writers, internal Web pros and White House folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Examples of the work and links to press clips, including a videos of Macon and Todd discussing the serendipity of my participation and the President using the site, are &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HealthCare.gov is not a Health Insurance Exchange. The Exchanges will be in place by 2014. Some states are working to get them up prior to that date. HealthCare.gov is two things. It is a informational site with lots of clarification on the law and the current state of HealthCare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps more significantly, &lt;strong&gt;it is also a one-stop shop for finding ALL the health insurance options available to you.&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to The Affordable Care Act, for the first time, insurance companies must report a whole slew of information about all of their plans and costs. This information is then pumped into HealthCare.gov via the the &lt;a href=&quot;http://finder.healthcare.gov&quot;&gt;Insurance Options Finder&lt;/a&gt;, which sorts through billions of available options, filters them down, and presents a manageable menu of options that are available to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a major first step. And it was launched in less than three months! Working with Macon, Todd, and the rest of the team was the most amazing and intense project of my career. The work was high stakes, fast-paced, intellectually fascinating, and most importantly, really meaningful. I worked on HealthCare.gov for five months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you send out your ideas into the world, you really don’t know what they will lead to.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently spoke with Brian Casel and Dave Yankowiak on their Web series &lt;a href=&quot;http://freelancejam.com/&quot;&gt;Freelance Jam&lt;/a&gt; about this and other projects - &lt;a href=&quot;http://freelancejam.com/10-behind-the-scenes-designing-a-government-website-used-by-millions/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watch the Show&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
